A Guide to the John D. Rockefeller 3rd Associates, Joan Dunlop papers FA252
Rockefeller Archive Center
John D. Rockefeller 3rd Associates, Joan Dunlop papers
1954-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Dunlop, Joan
FA252
14.5 Cubic Feet 37 hollinger boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open for scholarly research.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents note
The Joan Dunlop papers document her work as serving as an associate in the office of the Rockefeller Family and Associates from 1971-1979. This is not a collection of her personal papers.
These papers detail Dunlop’s important work in expanding John D. Rockefeller 3rd's population interests to include sexuality, sex education, family planning, and reproductive health and abortion rights.
These records include grants, contributions and gifts to broadened population interests, John D. Rockefeller 3rd’s statement made at the World Population Conference, 1974 in Bucharest, and testimony to the Select Committee on Population. Additionally the papers include the presidential search and selection of George Zeidenstein, and the reorganization of Population Council as well as the work of the Population Education, Inc. and its Project on Human Sexual Development.
The collection spans from 1954-1979 with the bulk of it representing John D. Rockefeller 3rd’s population interests from 1973 to 1978.
Biographical note
Joan Dunlop, a staff associate of John D. Rockefeller 3rd (JDR 3rd) from 1971-1979 with responsibility for his population interests played a vital role in broadening the scope of his population interests to include sexuality, sex education and reproductive health rights.
Dunlop was born in London on May 20, 1934. She attended Queens Secretarial College in London. After her schooling, she went to America and was hired by the Ford Foundation. She worked on urban policy projects that became the foundation for the Johnson’s administration’s War on Poverty. After working at the Ford Foundation she was employed in the New York City budget office under Major John V. Lindsay.
In the 1970s she served as an associate in the office of the Rockefeller Family and Associates.
Later on she became the president of the International Women’s Health Coalition and played a pivotal role in making women’s sexual and reproductive health rights a central tenet of the 1994 UN Conference on Population and Development in Cairo and the Women’s Conference in Beijing in 1995.
She died of breast cancer on June 29, 2012 in Lakeville, Connecticut.
Related Archival Materials note
Rockefeller Brothers Fund records, 1941-2003; John D. Rockefeller 3rd papers, 1906-1978; John and Mary R. Markle Foundation records; Commonwealth Fund records, SG 1 series 18; Agricultural Development Council, and Population Council records.
Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project, 1971-2006
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Joan Dunlop papers were donated to Rockefeller Archive Center as a work product of the John D. Rockefeller 3rd papers.
File Plan note
This collection was originally designated under the former classification III 17 H.
Arrangement note
The John D. Rockefeller 3rd Associates, Joan Dunlop papers are intellectually arranged into five subject based series, one of which has been divided into a subseries. No discernible original order of the collection as a whole existed. However, original order of the documents has been retained within each folder.
Series 1: Administrative Files (1971-1978)
Series 2: Agricultural Development Council (ADC) (1973-1979)
Series 3: Other Rockefeller philanthropies (1963-1979)
Series 4: John D. Rockefeller 3rd grants, contributions and gifts (1966-1978)
Series 5: Population (1954-1979) Subseries 1: Abortion (1971-1978); Subseries 2: Select Committee on Population testimony (1977-1978); Subseries 3: Population Council (PC) (1954-1979); Subseries 3.1: Administrative files (1954-1977); Subseries 3.2: Funding (1963-1979); Subseries 3.3: Nobel Peace Prize (1970-1972); Subseries 3.4: Presidendential search and reorganization (1959-1978); Subseries 4: Population Education, Inc. (PEI) (1972-1979); Subseries 4.1 Administrative files (1971-1979); Subseries 4.2 Project on Human Sexual Development (PHSD) (1972-1979); Subseries 4.3: Sex education (1969-1978); Subseries 4.4: Women and development (1974-1979); Subseries 4.5 World Population Conference, 1974 (1973-1976)
Family planning; Reproductive rights; Sex instruction; Sex; Reproductive health; Women and development; Abortion; Women's rights; United States; Population; Dunlop, Joan
- Administrative files, 1971-1978; 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 Administrative files, consists of time sheets, expense reports and monthly planners. These materials span from 1971 to 1978.
  - Allocation of time, 1971, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd account- miscellaneous and travel expense reports for Joan Dunlop, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd account- travel expense reports and calendar of Joan Dunlop for Bucharest trip, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd account- miscellaneous and travel expense reports for Joan Dunlop, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Monthly Calendar, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd account- miscellaneous and travel expense reports for Joan Dunlop, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd account- miscellaneous and travel expense reports, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd giving program, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Joan Dunlop trip to Asia expense reports, 1977 October 9-November 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd giving program, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd account- miscellaneous and travel expense reports, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd account- miscellaneous and travel expense reports for Selinda A. Melink, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Office of John D. Rockefeller 3rd expense reports of Joan Dunlop, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Press clippings- John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Irving, Levine - biographical sketch, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kaplan, Helen Singer, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ylvisaker, Paul Norman - resume, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Rockefeller Center Lunch Club Bills, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Monthly calendar planner, 1974 (Box 36, Folder 443)
- Agricultural Development Council (ADC), 1973-1979; 2
  Series 2, Agricultural Development Council (ADC), contains Joan Dunlop's work associated with the Agricultural Development Council in dealings with correspondence, program reviews, board meetings, and interests in Asia. These documents span from 1973 to 1979.
  - Agricultural Development Council and the role of women in agricultural development, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Boserup, Esther RE: Agricultural Development Council [EMPTY], undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Agricultural Development Council program review and evaluation, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Agricultural Development Council report for 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Potential contributors to Agricultural Development Council, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Visit to India and Philippines, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Women, agricultural development and World Bank program background for trip, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ravenholt, Marjorie S. RE: Agricultural Development Council, 1977 October (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The World Bank (John Simmons): RE: Agricultural Development Council, 1977 December (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Agricultural Development Council recruitment, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Epstein, T. Scarlett RE: Action-Oriented Study of the role of women in rural development in Asia, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Board of trustees meeting, 1978 June 12 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Board of trustees, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Committee for the Future, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Presidency, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Smith, Theodire McRoberts, 1974, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Trustee review committee draft report, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence from Bill Dietel to Joan Dunlop, 1978 June 28 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence from Michaela Walsh to Johnathan Silverstone, 1978 May 17 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence from John D. Rockefeller 3rd to Vernon W. Ruttan, 1976 March 11 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Board of trustees review of council program, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Interests in Asia, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Asian trip, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Agricultural Development Council; Conversation with Abe Weisblat, 1978 April 5 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Staff conference- Yogyakarta, Indonesia, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Ford Foundation information papers, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Agricultural and rural development, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Dayton, Alida R. correspondence about future of Agricultural Development Council, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Hopper, David The World Bank re: Agricultural Development Council, 1978 April (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Donor's meeting, 1978 April 17 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Wingspread Conference on Cooperatives, Small Farmers and rural development at Racine, Wisconsin (cancelled), 1978 April 24-26 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Other Rockefeller philanthropies and interests, 1963-1979; 3
  Series 3 Other Rockefeller philanthropies and interests, consists of materials with which John D. Rockefeller 3rd was associated with including corporate philanthropy, Asian philanthropy, and other Rockefeller philanthropies and interests. These materials span from 1963 to 1979.
  - Philanthropy- corporate, 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - JDR 3rd Fund, Inc., 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - JDR 3rd Fund, Inc. 12 year report, 1963-1977 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - JDR 3rd Fund, Inc. certificate of incorporation, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1973, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Dr. J. George Harrar successor, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Rockefeller Foundation reevaluation, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Population Council interests in China Medical Board, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Rockefeller Center, Inc., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Rockefeller Archive Center, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Rockefeller Public Service Awards program, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - JDR 3rd Fund, Inc., 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - TVTV - (Top Value Television), 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Environment, 1972-1973, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Advisory Board on Philanthropic Policy, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Citizen Involvement Network (CIN), 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Filer Commission [Empty], undated (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs, Filer Commission, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Smith, C. Datus, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Asian philanthropy, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 70)
- John D. Rockefeller 3rd grants, contributions and gifts, 1966-1978; 4
  Series 4 John D. Rockefeller 3rd grants, contributions, and gifts, consists of material regarding John D. Rockefeller 3rd's population interests in funding reproductive health rights defense funds, abortion rights and family planning. These documents span from 1966 to 1978.
  - WNET-Channel 13: Documentary film on Homosexual Life Styles, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Adair, Peter: Documentary film on Homesexual Life Styles, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Adair, Peter: "Who are we?": project, 1973, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Pan American Federation of Associations of Medical Schools, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges: documents, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Beasley defense contribution, 1966-1976 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Beasley defense correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Beasley defense correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - McCarthy, Abigail: Women's Conciliation Task Force, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - National Women's Political Caucus (NWPC): Pro-Choice Project (Hyde Amendment), 1977 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - National Women's Political Caucus (NWPC): Hyde Amendment, 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Center of Concern, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. (SIECUS), 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. (SIECUS) correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Preterm Institute, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Stuart, Martha: Communications for Change, 1970, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Stuart, Martha: Communications for Change correspondence, 1975-1976, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - National Women's Health Coalition: International Women's Year Project, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Planned Parenthood of New York City, Inc., 1973-1974, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Planned Parenthood: Justice Fund, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Planned Parenthood of Central Missouri, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL), 1976-1978 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL) Right to Life materials, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL): fundraising, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - American Civil Liberties Union Foundation (ACLU), 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights, 1975-1976, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights, 1976, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights: Women and the Law Conference, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - National Abortion Council (NAC) - correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - National Abortion Council (NAC), 1977 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - NAtional Abortion Council (NAC) - Atlanta meeting report, 1976 September 29- October 1 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - American Civil Liberties Union Foundation (ACLU), 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - The Alan Guttmacher Institute (AGI): fund raising, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - The Alan Guttmacher Institute (AGI) dispute, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Institute of Society, Ethics and the Life Science - grants, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - The Alan Guttmacher Institute (AGI): John D. Rockefeller 3rd grants, 1975, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Institute of Society, Ethics and Life Sciences - correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Institute of Society, Ethics and Life Sciences - documents, 1974 September (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Institute of Society, Ethics and the Life Sciences, 1976, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. - documents, 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Catholic Alternatives / Catholics for a Free Choice (CFFC), 1976 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Catholic Alternative / Catholics for a Free Choice (CFFC), 1976-1978 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Euthanasia [EMPTY], undated (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Office Strategy on Abortion, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - National Association of Abortion Facilities (NAAF) - meeting - Chicago, Illinois, 1976 November 12-14 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Edelin, Ken and post Bucharest related grants, 1974-1976 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Epstein, Scarlett / Nichols, Sandra, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Nicholas, Sandra - showing, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - Epstein, Scarlett / Nicholas, Sandra correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Epstein, Scarlett / Nicholas, Sandra documents, 1975, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - Epstein, Scarlett: Institute of Development Studies (IDS) Conference, University of Sussex, England; 9-12 December 1975, 1974, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Association for the Study of Abortion (ASA), National Abortion Federation (NAF), and National Abortion Council (NAC) correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Giving plan, 1974, 1972-1974 (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Contributions, 1972, 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - Contributions, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Contributions, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Giving interests - General Discussions, 1972-1975 (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - Contributions, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - Contributions, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd office strategy, 1973, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - General John D. Rockefeller 3rd giving program, 1978, 1973, 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Abortion / Reproductive Freedom, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - Abortion / Reproductive Freedom, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - Contributions, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - Youth Values and Conception Project, 1975-1976, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Family Planning / Population, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - Women and development, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - Women and development, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - Women and development, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - Family planning / population, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 142)
  - Women's Action Alliancee, Inc. - National Women's Conference, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 143)
  - Women's Action Alliance, Inc. - National Women's Conference, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 144)
  - Women's Action Alliance Exposition, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 145)
  - Women's Action Alliance, 1978 May 23-24 (Box 12, Folder 146)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the United States, Inc., 1969-1971 (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - Grant actions - John D. Rockefeller 3rd [disbounded binder], 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 179)
  - Grants, 1972, 1976, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 180)
  - International Women's Year (IWY) tribune - John D. Rockefeller Grant, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 181)
  - International Women's Year (IWY) - general correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 15, Folder 182)
  - International Women's Year (IWY) - background, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 183)
  - Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RGAR) - grants, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 184)
  - Relgious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR) - grants, 1970, 1972-1977 (Box 15, Folder 185)
  - Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR) - correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 15, Folder 186)
  - Zeidenstein, Sondra - grants, 1976-1978 (Box 15, Folder 187)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. (SIECUS), 1972-1973 (Box 16, Folder 190)
  - Citizens Committee on Population and the American Future, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 191)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the U.S. appeal, 1971-1975 (Box 16, Folder 192)
  - Family planning / population, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 193)
- Population, 1954-1979; 5
  Series 5 Population consists of five subseries, all of which are related to Joan Dunlop’s work as an advisor to John D. Rockefeller 3rd with regards to his population interests. Documents span from 1954-1979.
  Subseries 1: Abortion consist of funding plans, strategic policies, grants related to abortion and news clippings. Documents span from 1971 to 1978.
  Subseries 2: Select Committee on Population testimony contains John D. Rockefeller 3rd's testimony to the Scheuer Committee. Documents range from 1977 to 1978.
  Subseries 3: Population Council contains administrative files relating to Population Council; funding program efforts including program budgets, grants, and fundraising actions; Nobel Peace Prize consideration documentation; and presidential search and reorganization documentation including resumes and efforts to reorganize. Documents span from 1954 to 1979.
  Subseries 4: Population Education, Inc., consists of administrative files including funding and board meeting documentation. Second, the Project on Human Sexual Development records including John Gagnon fellowship files, the Cleveland Survey which was an empirical study of parental attitudes to their children's sexuality in Cleveland, Ohio, and a television project. Third, sex education and women and development are represented in this subseries as well. Lastly, this subseries contains files on the World Population Conference of 1974. These include the Population Manifesto, news clippings and correspondence concerning John D. Rockefeller 3rd’s statement at the World Population Conference in Bucharest. The documents range from 1954 to 1979.
  - Statement on Population by World Leaders, 1966 (Box 36, Folder 445)
  - Abortion, 1971-1978; 5.1
    - Right to Life, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 148)
    - Abortion, 1974-1976 (Box 13, Folder 149)
    - Abortion, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 150)
    - Abortion: A summary of the arguments, undated (Box 13, Folder 151)
    - Abortion / reproductive freedon - giving program, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 152)
    - Abortion funding strategy, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 153)
    - Abortion funding, 1973-1978 (Box 13, Folder 154)
    - Abortion "new strategy", 1973-1976 (Box 13, Folder 155)
    - Abortion strategy, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 156)
    - Strategy meeting on abortion: September, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 157)
    - Strategy meeting on abortion, troops meeting, 1976 September (Box 13, Folder 158)
    - Abortion memos, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 159)
    - Abortion - "Debate" - long hall, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 160)
    - Newspaper clippings: Abortion: Catholics, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 161)
    - History of foundation support on abortion, 1973-1977 (Box 13, Folder 162)
    - Study of attitudes of abortion and other issues, prepared for Ruderand Finn Inc. by Roper Organization, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 163)
    - Jimmy Carter and the Catholics, John D. Rockefeller 3rd and abortion, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 164)
    - United Methodist Church and the Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights (RCAR), 1974 (Box 14, Folder 164A)
    - American Civil Liberties Union Foundation (ACLU) - abortion proposals, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 165)
    - Abortion: Ruder, Bill, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 166)
    - General files - religious coalition, 1973, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 167)
    - Articles - abortion, 1974-1976 (Box 14, Folder 168)
    - Catholics on abortion, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 169)
    - Abortion strategy, 1973-1974, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 170)
    - Hyde Amendment: articles, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 171)
    - Medicaid abortion. John D. Rockefeller 3rd wires etc., 1978 (Box 14, Folder 172)
    - Polls, 1975-1976 (Box 14, Folder 173)
    - Pro-natalist aspects of laws relating to contraception, abortion, and voluntary sterilization in the United States by Pilpil, Harriet F. and Ames, Peter, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 174)
    - Population studies documents, 1974-1975 (Box 14, Folder 175)
    - Migration and immigration, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 176)
    - State department / aid, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 177)
    - Paul Simon: breakfast ideas, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 178)
    - Abortion - grantees, 1973-1978 (Box 16, Folder 194)
    - Grants: abortion, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 195)
    - Grant letters miscellaneous, 1970-1974 (Box 16, Folder 196)
    - Pro-natalist aspects of Laws Relating to Contraception on, Abortion, and Voluntary Sterilization in the United States, 1971 September 15 (Box 36, Folder 446)
    - Birth control clippings, 1974 (Box 37, Folder 453)
  - Select Committee on Population testimony, 1977-1978; 5.2
    - John D. Rockefeller 3rd testimony to Scheuer Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 188)
    - Scheuer Committee / Congress and Population, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 189)
    - Select Committee on Population - John D. Rockefeller 3rd testimony, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 444)
  - Population Council, 1954-1979; 5.3
    - Adminstrative files, 1954-1977; 5.3.1
      - World Leaders Declaration on Population, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 197)
      - Population Council - resumes, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 198)
      - Population Council, 1974-1976 (Box 16, Folder 199)
      - Population Council, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 200)